Combining Computational Analyses and Interactive
Visualization to Enhance Information Retrieval
Carsten Görg, Jaeyeon Kihm, Jaegul Choo, Zhicheng Liu, Sivasailam Muthiah,
Haesun Park, John Stasko
College of Computing, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA USA
ABSTRACT
Exploratory search and information-seeking support systems attempt
to go beyond simple information retrieval and assist people
with exploration, investigation, learning and understanding activities
on document collections. In this work we integrate several
computational text analysis techniques, including document summarization,
document similarity, document clustering, and sentiment
analysis, within the interactive visualization system Jigsaw
in order to provide a flexible and powerful environment for people
to examine sets of documents. Our focus is not on cutting edge
algorithms for computational analysis but rather on the process of
integrating automated analyses with interactive visualizations in a
smooth and fluid manner. We illustrate this integration through an
example scenario of a consumer examining a collections of car
reviews in order to learn more about the car and understand its
strengths and weaknesses.
Keywords
exploratory search, information seeking, sense-making, visualization,
visual analytics
1. INTRODUCTION
We have been developing new interfaces and systems for information
retrieval, in particular, for retrieval of collections of documents
with a goal of understanding the many different dimensions
and contents of those documents. Sometimes called Exploratory
Search [11, 5], Information Seeking Support [6], or Sense-making [4],
these processes go beyond the initial retrieval of data by providing
environments in which a person can browse, explore, investigate,
discover, and learn about the topics, themes, and concepts within
the documents.
More specifically, the following situations provide examples of
the types of processes we seek to support:
􀀀 A police investigator has a collection of case reports, evidence
reports, and interview transcripts and seeks to “put the
pieces together” to identify the culprits behind a crime.
􀀀 An academic researcher moves into a new area and seeks to
understand the key ideas, topics, and trends of the area, as
well as the set of top researchers, their interests, and collaborations.
Copyright is held by the author/owner(s).
HCIR’10, August 22, 2010, New Brunswick, NJ USA.
􀀀 A consumer wishes to buy a new digital camera but encounters
a large variety of possible models to choose from, each
of which with supporting documentation and consumer reviews.
􀀀 A family learns that their child may have a rare disease and
they scour the web for documents and information about the
condition.
Our approach combines two main components: automated computational
analysis of the documents and interactive visualizations
of the documents themselves and of the results of the analysis. Such
a combination is described as a visual analytics approach [9, 3]
and it attempts to leverage the strengths of both the human and the
computer. Humans excel at the interactive dialog and discourse of
exploration and discovery. They develop new questions and hypotheses
as more and more information is uncovered. The computer
excels at complicated analyses of large data collections to determine
metrics, correlations, connections, and statistics about the
document collection.
Relatively few systems to date, however, have smoothly incorporated
both automated computational analysis and interactive visualization
while providing a tight coupling between the two. It
is more common to encounter systems focused on one of the two
capabilities that also add a few elements from the other capability.
For instance, computational analysis tools sometimes provide
rudimentary user interfaces to access analysis capabilities. Alternatively,
interactive visualization systems may provide a few simple
techniques such as filtering or statistical analysis of the data.
The system through which we have been exploring this coupling
is Jigsaw [8], a tool for helping people explore document collections.
Jigsaw is a relatively mature prototype system, and has seen
initial use in the field by clients from law enforcement, investigative
reporting, fraud detection, and academic research, among others.
An initial user study with the system showed its potential in helping
investigators and supporting different analysis strategies [2].
Until now, Jigsaw has provided more in the way of interactive
visualization support of document exploration. In particular, Jigsaw
visualizes connections between entities across documents to
help investigators follow trails of information. Recently, we added
enhanced computational analysis to the system. Jigsaw now also
provides capabilities such as analysis of document similarity, document
sentiment, document clusters by theme or content, and document
summarization through a few words or sentences.
Our focus has not been about developing innovative new algo