Information visualization of the minority game
W Jiang1,2, R D Herbert2∗ and R Webber2
1Shanghai E&P International, Inc. 12&37F, Shanghai Information Tower, 211
Century Ave., Pu Dong New District, Shanghai 200120, China.
2School of Design, Communication and Information Technology, The University of
Newcastle, Australia
E-mail: Ric.Herbert@newcastle.edu.au
Abstract. Many dynamical systems produce large quantities of data. How can the system be
understood from the output data? Often people are simply overwhelmed by the data.
Traditional tools such as tables and plots are often not adequate, and new techniques are
needed to help people to analyze the system. In this paper, we propose the use of two spacefilling
visualization tools to examine the output from a complex agent-based financial model.
We measure the effectiveness and performance of these tools through usability experiments.
Based on the experimental results, we develop two new visualization techniques that combine
the advantages and discard the disadvantages of the information visualization tools. The model
we use is an evolutionary version of the Minority Game which simulates a financial market.
1. Introduction
One important factor concerning many models is that frequently large amounts of data are produced.
There is the research issue of how end-users can be presented with this data so that maximum benefits
can be attained from the data production. The usual approach like a series of tables or data series plots
can help people understand the simple model, but more advanced information visualization techniques
[8] are needed to show more complex relationships between multiple data attributes.
For example, many financial models produce massive quantities of data, and trying to understand
the interactions between the data and ‘what it all means’ is not a simple task. We ask the question of
whether information visualization can aid in the understanding of data from economic models.
In this paper we consider a particular class of information visualization techniques: space-filling
information visualizations; and we use data from a particular model: the Minority Game. In [5] we
applied existing space-filling visualization techniques to the output of the Minority Game. In [4] we
evaluated these techniques using experiments on end-users’ understanding of financial markets
modeled by the Minority Game. In this paper we present new space-filling techniques designed to
overcome shortcomings of the existing techniques identifier by these experiments.
2. The Model
The Minority Game [1,2] is a game consisting of several rounds where an arbitrary odd number of
players choose one of two possible options each round. The two options could be zero or one, A or B,
∗ To whom any correspondence should be addressed.
2007 International Symposium on Nonlinear Dynamics (2007 ISND) IOP Publishing
Journal of Physics: Conference Series 96 (2008) 012011 doi:10.1088/1742-6596/96/1/012011
c 2008 IOP Publishing Ltd 1
buy or sell, or any two things indicative of a competitive situation where there are two possible options
the agents involved can choose from at any given point in time.
Each round of the game results in a majority of players choosing one of the options. The players
who did not choose the majority option are in the minority and are the winners of that particular round.
Each player has a score, and their score increases when they win a round.
The number of winning players each round can range from 0 to (n-1)/2, for a game involving n
players. Each of the players can remember the winning option (the option chosen by the minority of
players) for the previous m number of rounds. This m represents the memory size of each player, and
is fixed for all players.
Each player is able to remember the previous m winning options, they also have a set of s strategies,
each of which determines what option they should choose for the current round based on the history of
previous winning options. For m rounds there are 2m possible winning histories – thus each strategy
has a size of 2m (one bit representing the option to choose for each of the possible winning histories).
There are many variations on the Minority Game. We consider players to be agents (companies) in
a financial market. Their score represents their capital stock. In our version of the game evolution
occurs periodically with losers being replaced with clones of those agents with the largest capital (the